so how do we implement the least
recently used policy that works really
well and it works really well because it
exploits locality the most recently used
thing is likely to be used very soon
afterwards the thing that we haven't
used for a while means that there is
less reason for locality to kind of
cause it to be accessed again let's say
we have a four-way set assertive cache
and let's just track what's happening in
this one set so there is four blocks in
it for each of these blocks we keep the
tag and the valid bit and in order to
track which block was accessed to when
we're going to also have an lru counter
for each block these counters take
values that correspond to the size of
the set in this case 0 through three
because there are four things in the set
so let's initialize them to 0 1 2 and
three they have to all be different all
the time and we will see how that is
maintained so we start like this when we
want to replace something
we will replace the block whose counter
is currently zero because that's going
to be the least recently used block so
let's say that we access some block a
and we need to put it somewhere we will
choose the place with a zero counter and
put it there now that the block is
placed there the processor accesses it
and suddenly this becomes the most
recently used block so its counter now
needs to be three in order to make sure
that all of the counter still have
different values that means that all of
the other counters now need to be
decremented so the one that was one
becomes zero two becomes one and three
becomes two and now let's say that we
access some Block B we put it here
because the counter is zero now here
when B is accessed after putting it here
that counter becomes three this one
becomes two this one becomes zero and
this one becomes one we will now put
some Block C here that becomes three
three this becomes two this becomes one
this becomes Zero D 3 2 1 0 now we're
back to this situation so I'm going to
clean up here and now if we access e
we're going to find what was the least
recently used block and a at this point
is because it's been accessed the least
recently so a will be replaced by E and
the lru counter here becomes three which
brings these one notch lower so this is
the state we have now let's say that b
which is the least recently used block
now is re accessed what happens then is
this counter needs to become three all
of the other ones now need to be changed
lower what happens if the most recently
block let's say B is accessed again then
this counter just stays at three because
that indicates that this is already the
most recently access block what happens
if block D which is neither the most nor
the least recent is accessed well this
counter needs to become three and now we
have an interesting situation we don't
just lower all the other counters a
notch down we take the ones that were
above the original value of this counter
so we take the counter that is above one
and those are the ones that get a notch
down but the ones that are below one
stay the same that ensures that the
counters still have different values
let's do another one of those where
let's say Block B that is almost the
most recently used block is accessed in
that case this counter needs to become
three all counters that were above its
original value of two need to be
decremented so this becomes two but
these two stay the same because they're
below two so again we have this
situation so now you know how to
maintain the lru counters properly
after every step you can
verify that the counters have different
values if they don't then you probably
made a mistake somewhere so as you can
see maintaining lru is relatively
complicated for an nway set asso of
cache we need n counters whose size is
log two of n in this case the size of
the counters is to bit because they need
to have a number between 0 and three to
tell us where are we in the order of
axis in this set so it's a fourway set
assive cash that means we need two bits
per counter and four counters so for
highly associative caches something like
32 way associative you would need to
have five bit counters and 32 of them
per set so this was the cost it's pretty
high worse there is an energy problem we
need to modify up to end counters on
each access even cash hits that can
happen very frequently so the lru
approximations try to keep fewer
counters and do fewer updates on cash
hits